[Music]
hello good evening and good day
everybody welcome to the latest episode
of the ask a budget show
today we discuss science astrophysics
and all that good stuff
so before we begin as always let me
greet you all and see who all is there
with us i can see crazy brain durga
nilesh
scranton beats swapna animish
and lots of other people good evening
good day all of you great to have you
all with me on this show
this fine day fine day fine evening
and let us get into the questions shall
we
let's get right into the questions
all right what do we have for today
um
kosh says why is it so hard for israel
to develop reusable rockets for our
missions instead of having to build
a new rocket every time
it is a very good question it's i'm sure
it's not hard
for isro to do uh to develop reusable
rockets
uh
it's just that most likely they have not
been
this sort of project may not have been
sanctioned by the higher ups by the
authorities see isro is a government
organization it's run by the government
its funding comes from the government
all the orders all the
all of that all the directions come from
the government of india
so they do what the government tells
them to do
right
um
um so yeah even i have asked this
question why doesn't isro do this
i mean uh
i'm sure it's not an easy technology to
develop but hey that's what engineers do
they take up difficult problems and they
solve those problems
i even uh heard that some amateur rocket
builder
tried this for a few years and he was
able to create a small
a small reusable rocket which would go
up and it was able to land successfully
back on earth
so i'm sure it's not that difficult the
problem especially when you have the
kind of
funding that isro has yeah i know
comparing an amateur rocket builder to
isro is not exactly the correct thing to
do
but overall the problem they are solving
is the same
so it's it's about a lack of ambition
from whoever is is is controlling this
rope right now what isro is doing it's
it's developing smaller rockets
what on earth is that for it it will
earn a few million dollars per year for
isro and for the country but
we need to think bigger
uh space exploration is
going to increasingly be one of the most
important
facets of geopolitical advancement in
the 21st century by the end of the 21st
century the two or three nations that
will
lead the world in space exploration are
going to be the 203 nations that lead
the world in everything
so it is important that isro goes in the
right direction we need to build more
powerful rockets we need to uh
build reusable rockets
i mean when spacex started first
trying to develop the technology people
laughed at it when spacex first entered
the space launch competition as a space
launch company people laughed at it
right it was very difficult but they
were able to
succeed on extremely small budgets
because it's an agile entrepreneurial
company it's run by one guy who has a
vision
and the kind of uh budget they had was
way way way lower lower than what
nasa
or lockheed martin or whoever else was
in the picture earlier it was way lower
than their budgets
and
and yet they were able to succeed and
when they said that they are building
they are trying to develop
re
uh reusable rockets people laughed at
them and yet they succeeded and now
they've gone beyond any what anybody
could imagine
so i think
i'm sure there are excellent we know
there are excellent engineers and
scientists in israel
and i'm sure some of them would want to
develop such technologies they need to
be empowered
that's what needs to happen we need to
empower our scientists so the the this
needs to happen at the leadership level
uh
so the government needs to take the
initiative i i don't think it's that
hard for israel to do it you give them
the funding you give them the go ahead
they can do it in the next two three
years maximum five years i'm sure they
can do it
but somebody i mean they need to be
allowed to do this
that is the problem in a government
organization everything needs
permissions and approvals and all that
and right now it's clear that they don't
have it
uh even even something like chandrayaan
i mean we had chandrayaan one in which
year was it 2008 910 somewhere there
then the next mission chandrayaan-2
happened in 2019
it was a partial success partial failure
i was hoping that within six months to
12 months they would do the next attempt
and yet here we are and we are still
waiting for that to happen it's it's i
don't know if it's gonna happen this
year or not so it's disappointing the
slow incredibly slow bureaucratic
governmental pace
at which
things are progressing
other nations are are forging ahead
the chinese are significantly ahead of
india right now the americans are
anywhere the leaders the russians have
very very good technology space
exploration technology the japanese are
doing well
yeah spacex a private company is ahead
of israel way ahead of israel now they
are developing the world's most powerful
rocket ever
a private company
yeah
and you have other private companies as
well like uh blue origin that are
already doing the same right they are
they also have reusable rockets rockets
that can land back
on the earth instead of having to
dump them in the ocean so everyone's
going far ahead and israel is just
crawling because the leadership doesn't
have the ambition as far as i can see
so there is disappointing i don't think
it's hard for isro to do this
you give them the right amount of
funding you give them the go ahead they
can do it
the next two to three years
i'm sure they can do it maximum five
years maximum reusable rockets and much
more
they already have the know-how to to
build much more powerful rockets
the technology already exists they just
need to be able to test it out a few
times
so it's just a question of government
approval and that's unfortunately what's
not happening as far as i can see i mean
obviously i am not privy to what's going
on behind the scenes the decision making
and whatever else but as an outsider
from what i observe it looks like there
is
these problems
are hampering israel and slowing things
down so
it's frustrating it's disappointing but
that's where we are i hope that things
change we have the potential to become
one of the top
space faring nations in the world why
not do it it doesn't cost that much of
money
so i hope
things change yeah because we have the
ability and the potential to be in the
top two top three for sure
right next question
nikhil says recently i have read
somewhere that a photo of a ufo
spotted in scotland in 1990s was found
and also read that the particular photo
was lost in the last 30 years and now it
has been unveiled
how much truth is this and what's your
opinion about this okay let's take a
look at the photograph i think it's
called the calvin photograph right let
me see let me let me google that
alvin photograph
and let us put that on the screen
what does this ufo picture look like
what does google tell us
let's see let's go to images
and apparently this is the best picture
that we have of ufos thus far this uh
gentleman is holding up the picture and
if you want the details of the picture
it looks something like this
so this apparently is the best
ufo picture that we have that has ever
been taken
it happened in this place called calvin
in scotland north of edinburgh and
glasgow
and
somebody took this image so you have
what appears to be an unidentified
flying object a ufo
uh in the background you have hills
and you also have an aircraft flying in
the background
so it looks like the ufo is
it appears to be between the observer
the photographer and the aircraft the
aircraft seems to be uh somewhat further
away than this
object the flying object the ufo
is this no this is
is this also that i'm not sure
so there seem to be multiple versions of
this photograph around but this is the
one i have seen earlier yes
yeah so this is the photograph that we
are referring to the calvine photograph
so the question is um
so apparently this was taken somewhere
sometime in the 1990s maybe in 1990 and
uh
it wasn't lost what i read is that the
photograph had been suppressed
so the government the authorities or
whoever it was uh
apparently the people the persons
apparently there were two people
two individuals
who took the photograph
and then they submitted it to a
newspaper or some media outlet for
publication
but instead of publishing it this
newspaper or whoever magazine or
whatever it was
they uh alerted the authorities
the authorities apparently confiscated
the picture and it was suppressed for
the longest time
so that is what i hear
and that seems to indicate that this is
something genuine something explosive
something that the public should not
have been allowed to see or something
like that that's the kind of impression
that this story gives us
so and and now for some reason they have
unveiled it revealed it or allowed it to
be published and apparently those two
people who took the photograph their
identities are still not revealed and
they will be kept secret for the next i
don't know
two three decades maybe five decades i'm
not sure what uh what the time period is
but their identities are uh have been
suppressed they've been
concealed i i don't know why it is so
maybe to to keep up the appearance that
this is something very secretive and
something very uh confidential or
whatever i'm not sure what it is so what
is my opinion about this my opinion
about this is is that i am very
skeptical about this this one picture
proves nothing
so i read that the experts have said
that this is the most authentic looking
picture and it doesn't look like it's
been
it's been photoshopped or or manipulated
or anything it appears to be the genuine
thing but look i am no expert in
photography and what i see over here
well it's
it's certainly not very grainy it is a
better resolution picture than what you
typically get from you about ufos yeah
and yet
it doesn't tell me much
i can't really
i can't really make a judgment as to
whether it's genuine or not
it looks like a craft that
could be hovering in the air but i i
beyond that i don't know see the only
this is not really a clinching evidence
of ufos this is not clinching evidence
in my opinion of alien visitation to the
planet or any such activity the
clinching evidence is as if
multiple people from multiple angles see
the same phenomenon take pictures or
video of it and it all appears
in in social media or news everywhere
why why is it always just one picture
why is it always just one angle
and why does it always happen in
english-speaking countries
yeah
so
for me what would represent clinching
evidence would be
multiple
sources photographing or taking video of
the same phenomenon same event yeah
or
finding an actual ufo and having
journalists visit it
or maybe
interviewing an
actual alien something like that
something that is genuine beyond any
shadow of a doubt
that is what would convince me this
unfortunately does not convince me
it could be genuine but it could also be
you know faked
so this does not convince me i am
hopeful and you know what i actually am
pretty sure
that uh alien civilizations exist beyond
our
solar system
i'm pretty convinced about that there
are so many stars galaxies trillions
gazillions bazillions of them yeah
it's it's almost a mathematical
certainty it's almost a statistical
certainty that there is
life beyond our planet maybe in our old
solar system microbial life or so and
there there could be intelligent life
elsewhere i'm pretty certain it should
it should be almost a certainty yeah
but thus far
i have seen no actual clinching evidence
that convinces me i am a skeptical
person that's my that's what i am by
training and by by
that's just the way i am yeah it's not i
don't i'm not easy to convince so i am
not convinced by what i see it's
interesting
and here it looks like they are drip
feeding one thing at a time a couple of
years ago the us government got involved
and they started taking ufo seriously
apparently in the 1960s 1780s they used
to put people in mental asylums for
saying that they had been abducted
abducted by aliens or they had seen ufos
people were scared to speak about this
now it's the opposite thing
now they're taking it seriously and
they're announcing various
investigations into the ufo phenomenon
they're calling it
uaps or whatever they're calling it now
they're rebranding it
yeah and these things only appear in the
english-speaking world only in the
mostly in the uh north american region
so you know it it looks like it's all
fabricated to me
this this it looks very fishy i'm not
convinced i i get the feeling that they
are trying to create this
new trend
to divert attention from something else
maybe i'm not sure what it is yeah so my
take is very simple i am not convinced
this does not convince me
there there you are
sorry
okay vinai vinai man says what's your
take on the 2400 no 24 000 year old
zombie viruses
revived and cloned in the arctic
permafrost
what do we mean by the arctic permafrost
shall we see what there is
we need to see a map because maps are
important right we need to see the map
so where is the map here's the map
here's the map
come on up here here we are so let's
take a look at the satellite image
what's it look like
so if you go far north
yeah
if you go far north
you will see snow and ice here
so these are the arctic regions of our
planet near the north pole
um
and these regions are essentially
permanently under snow for some reason
it's not showing me snow right now here
maybe global warming has gone too far
i'm not sure what it is
this should all be covered in snow and
frost but here we are we have some of
that here this is some zeldmia zimlia
this is novaya zimlia it's where the
tsar bomba was tested
so uh
in the arctic regions what we find is
that
above a certain latitude
the ground
is permanently frozen
permanently frozen
and it's been this way uh for thousands
of years
now
the thing is this
you've had animals roaming around these
places for tens of thousands of years
mammoths ancient wolves ancient various
other animals birds species and other
species of animals maybe human beings
and you would also have ancient
microorganisms and these animals would
have lived there and died there and if
such animals died in these regions they
would
be frozen
and they would be buried under snow over
thousands of years yeah
that's what would happen so above a
certain latitude the ground is
permanently frozen and that is what we
call
permafrost
so it's entirely possible and we
discover mammoths and other animals
ancient horses etc very well preserved
very nicely frozen etc we discover these
animals in these regions from time to
time every year we get some news of some
new animals being discovered here right
by various explorers and all that
researchers etc
but now because of global warming some
of this permafrost is thawing
it is slowly becoming unfrozen
and when something unfreezes things that
have been frozen
especially microorganisms they can come
back to life
when it comes to animals if you freeze
them they die
and if you unfreeze them if you throw
them they cannot come back to life in
the case of microorganisms that's not
always the case
in the case of plants and their seeds
again that's not the case a frozen seed
can sometimes be sprouted after
thousands of years i mean i think some
such experiment was actually conducted
so uh the issue is this ancient
microorganisms
could come back to life as the
permafrost starts thawing because of
global warming now climate change is a
natural thing it's also a man-made thing
there are these cycles of climate change
there are ice ages there are warmer
times
there is a cycle
it's called the milkano which cycles 100
000 or so years you have ice ages then
you have a time in which there is the
greenhouse effect which warms up the
planet then again you have ice ages and
so on so forth so that's a natural cycle
but now we are contributing something
because of the amount of carbon we are
emitting into the atmosphere that's
contributing to the warming up of the
planet in the atmosphere so because of
this global warming which has a natural
component and also a manmade component
uh the permafrost is slowly throwing in
the arctic regions yeah and because of
that
ancient viruses and ancient bacteria may
come back to life and that is what vinay
is referring to as zombie viruses i'm
not sure why the number twenty four
thousand years is given it could be
fifty thousand it could be ten thousand
we don't know
so yeah this could happen
ancient bacteria ancient diseases could
emerge again
um maybe you had some animal that died
of ancient disease that is no longer
prevalent but now if it
emerges again from from the permafrost
and thaws
then those bacteria may again be
reactivated and they could infect other
animals possibly or even humans if they
come come across the dead body of the
animal so these
scenarios are very plausible now
as as the permafrost thaws these
scenarios are plausible so i don't know
what you mean by reviving and cloning no
one's cloning anything
it's just that these frozen
microorganisms
may unfreeze the method and they may
become active again so there is no
cloning business happening there no
cloning phenomenon it's just a
reactivation and reviving
of ancient microorganisms here's the
thing
microorganisms are very hard to kill
people have drilled deep below the
earth's surface
layers of sediments that are millions of
years old
which would have been exposed on the
surface of the planet millions of years
ago and even when they drilled deep into
the bedrock of the earth
at a depth of millions of years they are
still able to find bacteria there
bacteria that have been encased in the
rock
for millions of years bacteria that were
dormant almost dead but not quite dead
so bacteria are capable of becoming
dormant for incredibly long amounts of
time millions of years
and that is scary
so a few thousand years in the
permafrost ten thousand twenty thousand
fifty thousand is nothing for them
so we could see
these
scenarios becoming true and that is
scary because we don't know what
diseases existed in the past in the
distant past
we don't know uh what bacteria may have
been around
and if they are revived
and if if our species homo sapiens has
never been exposed to that
that could be problematic it would mean
that we don't have immunity to that
typically
we develop a certain amount of natural
immunity to most diseases because our
ancestors came in contact with those
diseases again and again
for tens of thousands of years some of
them may have died some of them may have
survived and if you survive you develop
some kind of your body develop some sort
of some sort of understanding
at the cellular level
of that disease and sometimes that gets
passed on over the generations
so uh
if such a bacteria if such bacteria
species are there which we have never
encountered before that could be very
dangerous for us
so yeah this scenario is possible it is
plausible and
i hope it doesn't happen but we should
be prepared for it
swapnil says what gives the different
metals their individual colors such as
gold yellow copper brown aluminum gray
among others
are they naturally found in these colors
in their respective ores
or are they artificially coated there is
no artificial coating you take a piece
of gold let's say let's say
hypothetically gold if you are so rich
here
let's say you are extremely rich you
have a brick of gold
and you take a saw and you slice it
so if you slice it it will be in two
pieces and still the sliced part which
you cut open that will be the same color
so there's no coating it's actually that
color
and the same goes for other
uh metals
yeah
so where does this color come from yeah
why is this shirt the color it is why is
the background in these colors why is it
so it's not only about metals it's about
everything why is this black
so color that we perceive we perceive
different colors what are these colors
color is an illusion
color is something simply an illusion
you take a metal
and you see it through a microscope
you will see the the surfaces enlarge
but you can't see the atoms and
molecules but if you take an electron
microscope and you go deeper and deeper
inside you will start seeing eventually
individual molecules and individual
atoms
and you will not see them in any color
because atoms
don't have color color color has no
meaning at the quantum level at the
at the sub at the atomic and sub atomic
level so what is color
color is simply
electromagnetic radiation of various
wavelengths of frequencies
so if my shirt is blue
it means that it's absorbing
red
and
red and green frequencies of light and
it's emitting
it's it's reflecting the blue blue
frequency and it's absorbing everything
else
this black microphone
the fact that it is black
indicates that it's absorbing light in
all the different wavelengths it's
emitting almost nothing back back that's
why it looks black
my background over here is reddish
which means that it's it's
it's absorbing everything except for
brownish reddish
wavelengths of light
so that is what
gives creates the illusion of color
in reality color is just wavelengths
of electromagnetic radiation of photons
photons of various wavelengths and our
mind
interprets these different wavelengths
or frequencies is various colors it
color codes
electromagnetic radiation
in reality there is no color
it's just something that our mind
creates to help us make sense of the
of the universe
because if you had to actually see
individual frequencies it would be too
much information for you to process in
real time
so what the
our our senses do is that they simplify
the universe for us and give us a
dumbed-down picture so that we can
well make sense of it in real time
if there is too much information to
process then we cannot
function properly yeah
so what gives metals the individual
colors is that every single
metal
absorbs
electromagnetic radiation
of certain frequencies and it
reflects certain frequencies of light
and those frequencies
end up telling us what the colors are
right
so when it comes to uh
gold it absorbs
all the frequencies except for the
yellowish and golden yellowish
frequencies so those yellowish
wavelengths of light are reflected back
and that's why we see that sort of that
color of light coming back back at us
and that's why we feel that gold is
yellow
yeah that's how it is
so that is how it works that's how
that's the simplest explanation i can
give you
astra says
why are indians shorter in height is it
because of british colonization for 200
years
i am 5.6 inches exactly father's height
and about to 10 17 in october can i grow
taller apart from genetics perspective
why are indians shorter in height have
you seen me
i know i sit over here so you can't see
my exact size but i'm not exactly short
in height and i'm indian
but yeah if you if you look at the
average uh
demographic uh
statistical thing
indians seem to be
currently somewhat shorter than
people from let's say
uh the netherlands or
or or europe so certain european nations
indians on average i believe are taller
than the chinese and eastern asian
people or whatever yeah
so why is it so
is it because of british colonization
um
it has there are multiple factors when
it comes to your height
if you look at historical data
they found i mean
archaeologists or historian
archaeologists discovered a bunch of
skeletons i believe in the ganga valley
skeletons that date back to the deep
stone age around around 30 000 years
before today
and the average height of the skeletons
indian skeletons obviously was about
five eleven or six feet
so your ancestors were ridiculously tall
the average height was about six feet
almost yeah
so it's not always been this way so why
is it so so the truth is in the past 200
300 300 years
indians india's gdp dropped
dramatically
right india became
a ridiculously impoverished nation
every year there were famines created
artifa artificial famines created by the
british based on the irish model they
had created this artificial family in
ireland and they liked what they saw so
they recreated that in india year after
year after year so that indians could
not fight back and could not resist
british occupation of india so
when you go through 200 300 years of
near starvation
you
your food habits change
your body tries to conserve as much
energy as possible and that's why you it
tends to
give you shorter people yeah
and because of these two 300 years of
extreme deprivation of of privations of
of starvation
the food habits of indians also changed
and they became very frugal
so even today i see people eat very less
and and the food habits are not great
there is very little protein that people
eat i'm not saying you should eat meat
there are plenty of protein sources even
for vegetarians
so it's up to you i mean you want to eat
meat you eat meat the thing is this
the food habits changed in the past 300
years
and the the effects of the famines
obviously did contribute so that is the
reason why indians are right now shorter
in height even after 1947 until the
1990s until the 21st century india was a
very poor nation india is still a third
world nation
as
your lifestyle improves
as your diet improves you're gonna get
taller
it will take another two three
generations i can already see younger
kids they're already taller than kids in
the previous generations i can see that
so i think overall
it's it's because of the effects of the
past 300 or so years of foreign
occupation and destruction of india now
your height is 5.6 you're 17.
i think typically
people keep growing until they're
19 or 20 years old i think around 19
depending on various factors
so if you want to maximize your
potential see everybody has the maximum
potential height that they can achieve
based on genetics
and then whether you achieve that full
height or not depends on your lifestyle
do you eat a good diet or not do you
sleep enough or not do you exercise or
are you physically active or not
if you live a very sedentary lifestyle
no exercise no running around no outdoor
activity and if you have a poor diet
you're not gonna grow at all
but if you do
work out regularly if you do uh
indulge in athletic athletic activities
if you have a good diet you will reach
your hopefully your genetic potential
whatever it is i don't know what it is
here
so that's what i would say you want to
grow taller become physically active go
to the gym lift weights run every day
yeah and eat good food
healthy balanced diet lots of vegetables
and
a good amount of protein and calcium
yes
a good balanced diet and don't eat less
indians for some reason eat very less i
see them eat this much food like a
little sparrow
eat
so that's what i can tell you i don't
know your specific case i don't know
what your genetics are everybody has a
different set of genes
but yeah
overall that's the thing be physically
active
lift weights run a lot
and eat good food and sleep well
all right sir all the best
karthik says what is quantum tunneling
how can a
particle teleport faster than the speed
of life itself um
let's talk about quantum tunneling i
don't think i've taken this question
before interesting here
so quantum tunneling okay let's say i
have a ball yeah i've got a tennis ball
i have a wall here
this is the wall this is my ball if i
throw the ball here
it'll bounce off the wall and it'll go
back in this direction right
it will
every single time if i throw the ball at
a wall if i throw it at the wall it will
hit the wall and bounce back towards me
that is what we will observe a hundred
times out of 100 a million times out of
a million the ball hits the wall and
comes back
this is what we observe in the real
world but the real world is stranger
than what we think
when we go back to the deep
ultra microscopic level to the atomic
and subatomic level
of the
universe things are very different
at the quantum level
if you have a quantum wall
and you shoot a particle at it
there is
a finite non zero probability
that the particle may end up on the
other end other side of the wall
on the other side of the
barrier we call it a potential barrier
so this is a problem that you learn in
your abc level quantum mechanics
uh one dimensional potential barrier
yeah
so potential barrier is like a wall and
you have a particle coming in from one
direction
and you have to calculate the
probabilities you do you do solve the
one dimensional time dependent
schrodinger equation yeah
and and see what are the probabilities
of the of the wave function being on
this side of the wall and that side of
the wall and you find that the
probability of the particle being on the
other side of the wall is non-zero it is
lower than being on this side but it is
non-zero
so that is quantum tunneling sometimes
in quantum mechanics a particle can go
through a wall right through a wall
yeah which we can't do in the real world
i mean in the in the macroscopic world
so that is quantum tunneling and it's
not just some illusory effect it
actually happens
it actually happens
we have quantum tunneling diodes we have
uh
what was of what is that the the
tunneling scanning tunneling electron
microscope that uses this effect the
quantum tunneling effect even when it
comes to black holes hawking radiation
hawking radiation can be calculated as a
tunneling turning effect quantum
tunneling effect yeah so it actually
happens so in the quantum world at the
ultra microscopic subatomic level
particles can actually go through walls
so that in in
in brief
roughly
is what quantum tunneling is the quantum
world is incredibly strange bizarre it
doesn't make any sense what happens in
the quantum world
doesn't make any sense intuitively to us
which is why quantum mechanics when you
first come across it is quite a shock
especially if you if you're used to the
uh classical physics all right so that
is what quantum tunneling is
to understand simply it's essentially
quantum particles
electron or proton or whatever
going through an actual wall right
through it like a ghost
so that can happen so that is what
quantum tunneling is
lakshay says the rate of a formation of
stars in a galaxy depend on which
factors
right the rate of formation of stars in
a galaxy
it depends on how much molecular
hydrogen you have in a certain galaxy
and not just diffuse molecular hydrogen
but
molecular hydrogen clouds
i think they're called molecular clouds
or something like that so
so typically what you have
is
if you see a galaxy let's take the milky
way for instance
most of the milky way is empty space
but it's not entirely empty space it's
not a perfect vacuum you do have a
diffuse very very very diffuse gas
in this vacuum and most of it is just
hydrogen but it is not molecular
hydrogen it is ionized hydrogen
what is ionized hydrogen it's where you
strip away the electron from an atom
so when you ionize an atom it means you
have stripped away one or more electrons
and in the case of the hydrogen atom you
just have one electron it's a proton
surrounded by one electron so you strip
away that one electron you're left with
a hydrogen nucleus which is nothing but
a proton so typically in
in outer space in interstellar space
you've got this very diffuse gaseous
medium which is protons and electrons
essentially that's what it is ionized
hydrogen
now when you have a gas
of ionized hydrogen that cannot
cause star formation for star formation
to happen you need molecular hydrogen
hydrogen molecules
which is essentially atoms but you know
a molecular cloud
and these clouds need to uh
be cold
not hot
if it's a hot cloud it will have this
outward
it will have this uh outward push which
will prevent uh
the gravitational accumulation from
happening and all that so you need
molecular clouds with dust and which are
cool enough so let me show you what a
molecular cloud looks like since we are
talking about this
uh molecular cloud
pillars of creation
so very
um very famous
picture
let me show you what it looks like
i am showing you the map for some reason
let me
let me end that and let me bring in
the molecular clouds that i wish to show
you
here we are these are called the pillars
of creation
these are examples of molecular clouds
so these are essentially stellar
nurseries these are where new stars baby
stars are born
and if you look at this image
these are like three fingers
each of these three fingers is
if you look at the tips of these fingers
even the tips of these fingers are
larger than the entire solar system that
we live in
we think the solar system is huge it is
smaller than the tips of these fingers
so these are examples of molecular
clouds these are star forming regions
this is a zoomed in image of that
and let me show you some other molecular
clouds
these are various molecular clouds and
these are this is where stars are formed
these are stellar
nurseries
as you can see you can see them stars
being born in here
right
so
now to answer your question now that you
understand what are the conditions you
need for star formation the rate of
formation of stars in a galaxy depends
on how many
molecular clouds you have and whether
you have molecular clouds or not
so i think in the milky way the rate of
star formation per year must be like
four or five per year maybe in the
entire milky way we don't have that
higher rate of star formation in the
milky way in some some galaxies and some
regions of space you have lots of stars
being born on a
continuous basis
so you need these clouds for such a
thing to happen otherwise you will not
have star formation
all right sir
current says how do scientists measure
the mass of our galaxy as it also
contains empty space
let's talk about how to measure the mass
of any galaxy let's talk about a galaxy
that's far away let's say we want to
measure the mass of the in andromeda
galaxy
it's about what how far is it 1.5
million light years away or so yep
so first of all we have to understand
how far it is from us
we have to first understand the distance
of the galaxy from us now how do we
estimate the distance that how far a
galaxy is from us so there are certain
techniques we use one of them is the
standard candles the type 1a supernova
we know what is the the relation between
the luminosity of a type 1 a supernova
and the distance
so based and these supernovae happen on
a regular basis right
so from time to time you will see these
standard candles light up in galaxies so
when that happens you measure the
luminosity of the standard candle the
type 1a supernova
how much light are we getting from there
and based on that we can estimate to a
very good approximation what the
distance is to the galaxy so now we know
once we do this now we know how far this
galaxy is from here we know the distance
to a good approximation we know the
distance
now how do we measure the mass of the
galaxy so we see what is the total light
output how much light are we getting in
total from the galaxy that gives us an
approximation we know the distance how
far it is and now we know how much light
is coming out so based on that we can do
certain calculations and give get a good
approximate idea of how much visible
matter is in the galaxy
so we now have a good idea of totally
what is the total number of stars based
on the approximate average
luminosity of one star
and the amount of total immunity we're
getting we can
get a rough approximation of how much
how many stars there are and what is the
total visible mass of the galaxy
then
we look at the rate of rotation
of the galaxy how is it how is it
rotating how fast is it rotating now
galaxies rotate
for us they rotate very slowly so how do
we determine the rotation rate of a
galaxy speed of a galaxy
a galaxy let's say it's like this it's
like a disc here you see the light at
one end and you see the light at the
other end which end is red shifted which
end is blue shifted and then based on
the amount of redshift and blue shift we
have we can measure how fast the galaxy
is rotating
and based on how fast we are the galaxy
is rotating we can plot that on the
rotation curves and we can determine
how much
dark matter
is there around the galaxy we can
determine the size of the dark matter
hello of the galaxy so this is a rough
idea that i'm giving you of how we do
this
right so that's how we can determine how
far a galaxy is how much visible matter
is inside a galaxy and how much dark
matter it contains and of course there
are other things we can do we can see
how much gravitational lensing it is
producing that also gives us an idea of
how much matter dark matter this galaxy
contains
apart from the visible matter and of
course this is something that takes a
lot of time you can't just take a few
photographs and get an idea it takes
years
to get an approximate idea of how large
a galaxy is and how far it is from us
and as the decades go by we can refine
our understanding based on new data that
comes in
so astronomy is not something you can do
like
in a couple of days takes years
sometimes decades you have to look at
old data that previous generations of
astronomers have compiled and based on
all this data that we have we can
then uh
arrive at good at a good idea of how far
a galaxy is and how much mass it
contains in some cases uh some galaxies
are really far away and we may not have
a very good idea but some closer
galaxies like the andromeda galaxy in
the large and small majority cloud etc
we have a very good idea of uh
of these parameters yeah so that's how
you typically do it when it comes to
measuring the
mass of a galaxy and how much dark
matter it contains and things like that
right and similarly for our own galaxy
we can do such things
for our galaxy it is slightly difficult
because we can't see the entire galaxy
but once again we can do these things we
can see how many uh how much luminosity
is there
and things like that and over time
because we have
many many decades of data we can do the
calculations and approximately
understand how much
mass our galaxy also contains and how
much dark matter it may be there within
our galaxy so that's how it's done it's
not an exact science because there are
there is there are so many parameters
involved and there is so much we can't
see especially
when it comes to all galaxy but over the
years we've been able to do it well
okay mr jesus
mr jesus
uh asks me
what exactly is an ice age we were never
taught this concept in our curriculum
please help please explain
an ice age is a periodic phase in the
history of our planet in which
there is a period
of extensive glaciation
on the surface of the planet which means
that
the
there is a it's a time period
essentially it's a cyclical process
right
the cycles
last millions of years there are also
smaller cycles that last about 10 about
100 000 years and even within an ice age
you have periods of glaciation and
periods when the glaciers retreat but an
ice age
if you look at the entire history of the
planet is a period when the temperatures
are on average significantly colder like
seven eight nine degrees on average
colder than than otherwise
and it's a period when you have
extensive glaciation on the planet
apart from the equator
most of the other regions would be
covered under ice or snow lots of
glaciers and that sort of thing
so typically it's a period of time
when the average temperature
is
between seven to ten roughly degrees
lower than
when there is not an ice age all right
so that is essentially what it is
an ice age so we are currently within an
ice ages actually it may not feel like
that but we are within
an extended ice age right now we are not
in a period of glaciation the last
glacial maximum happened about 22 000
years before today
so about 22 000 years before today we
were at the last glacial maximum
when the glaciers and the ice coverage
on the surface of the planet was at its
maximum then slowly the glaciers receded
they started melting the sea water level
sea levels started rising then about 12
000 years before today there was this uh
sudden onset of
a small period of glaciation it's called
the younger dryas when again
uh the earth became cold for
a couple of thousand years or so
and then
we had these melt water pulses and this
the temperature started rising again and
right now we are in this period of
global warming
because of uh
various factors including human mediated
global warming human contribution to the
amount of carbon particles that are in
the atmosphere and so on so that's how
it is but overall to answer your
question an ice age is a time when the
average temperature across the planet is
significantly lower than otherwise
and it's a cyclical process all right
okay swapnil says what's the
inverse square law and how is it related
to the concept of gravity
what is the inverse square law
well it's it's a it's a concept in which
a property
let's say a force
is proportional
to the square of another to the
to the inverse of the square of any
other quantity so let me give you a
couple of examples yes um
so i can give you a couple of examples
one is the coulomb low coulomb's law of
electrostatics and one is the
gravitational law so let's let's put
that on the uh
on the screen what does it look like
coulomb's law
coulombs law
and let's put that on the screen so that
you understand what that means
so what does the equation for coulomb's
law look like
well here it is
let me make put a larger there you are
f equals k q 1 q 2 upon r square what
does that mean this essentially tells
you that the magnitude of the
electrostatic force
of attraction or repulsion yeah between
two point charges
is proportional
to
it is directly proportional to the
inverse
uh
it's
directly proportional to the
product
of the two charges and inversely
proportional to the square of the
distance between
between the two charges that's what it
is telling you so k is the constant of
proportionality over here k is the
constant of proportionality
so this is the coulomb load now let's
look at take a look at the
newtonian law of gravitation
newton's law newton's law of gravitation
love gravitation here we are
so once again you have a very similar
thing f equals g m1 m2 upon r squared
which means that the force is
directly proportional to the product of
the two masses and inversely
proportional to the square of the
distance between the two
so
one upon r squared this thing when you
whenever you have it it's an inverse
square law so this is how it is related
to the concept of gravity this is the
newtonian
the newton's law of gravity
and this is a good approximation of how
gravity actually works if you want a
better approximation you can
you will have to take a look at general
relativity so that's what it is the
inverse square law and how it is related
to the concept of gravity
aditya says if there are big cats
why are there no big dogs
yeah that's an interesting question
right so we have a whole lot of big cats
we have the regular house cat you have
leopards you've got cheetahs you've got
tigers you've got lions
and you've got jaguars and
various other kinds of big cats in the
past we had the sabre toothed tigers and
various other
big cats that have gone extinct
yeah so we had that why do we not have
big dogs do we have any let me see
uh what are the candids
see in ideas cannons
okay let me put that on the screen
so these creatures are called the canids
you have the dingo which is the
australian doggy
uh australian wild dog and various other
jackal-like animals
uh foxes jackals wolves
various kinds of dogs
you have indian candidates like the dole
dog which is a red colored dog
and then you have the indian jackal the
indian wolf
the himalayan wolf and so much more
but the question is why don't we have
giant big
big ones like like we have big
cats
so the thing is this
there are animals that are closely
related to the dog
such as for instance
let me see i if you want to look at the
taxonomy etc we have to go into this the
details
so we have candids then we have
so
canniformia these are various animals
that are related to dogs
the bear the raccoon
the seal
uh the
walrus and so on various kinds of bears
bears various raccoons
seals walruses i would say even
porpoises and veils
are related to dogs right so here are
your big dogs the panda also right
so the bear look at the bear's face what
does the bear's face look like it looks
like a dog right
and even if you see the the seals they
they have this barking voice the bark
seals at least some seals bark
so these are your big dogs they don't
exactly quite look like
dogs in the conventional sense the way
the big cats look like our house cats
but these animals over here are closely
related to dogs they are part of the
same evolutionary
uh branch family branch yeah
and they all have common ancestors
so you could consider a bear to be a big
dog you could consider
a walrus to be a big dog you could
consider a veil to be a distant relative
a kind of
water-based big dog
that's how it is it's it's
you you once you start observing it from
that angle you will understand you will
realize there are similarities
okay vine gaming says what is apogee and
perigee
when you have
an orbit let's say you have the earth in
orbit around the sun
now
the earth's orbit around the sun
is not a perfectly circular orbit
it's an elliptical orbit what is an
ellipse it's like a squashed circle you
take a circle and you squash it you get
an ellipse
right
so
the earth goes around the sun in an
elliptical orbit let's put that also on
the screen shall we
um
apogee perigee so when you have an
elliptical orbit
let's put that on the screen
so you get an idea
here we are so let's take a look at this
is this okay this is the earth sun
system yes
so when you have this elliptical orbit
the
earth will have up
in the orbit
there will be a point where the earth
comes the closest to the sun
and on the other end of the orbit you
will have a point where the earth is the
farthest from the sun
so the apogee is the furthest place from
the sun and the perigee is the closest
place to the sun
let's see over here perigee of the earth
moon system also has the same thing the
moon doesn't go around the earth in an
exactly circular orbit the moon's orbit
around the earth is also
elliptical
so there is a point in this orbit where
the moon comes closer to the earth and
there is a point in the orbit where it
is at the furthest so the furthest point
is the apogee the closest point is the
pedigree the same goes for satellites i
mean if you have a satellite in an
elliptical orbit if it's a polar orbit
it's not the case there are various
kinds of orbits of satellites around the
earth
but that's how it goes so this is the
apogee and the perigee this diagram i
think it shows you very well the perigee
is the closest point the apogee is the
furthest point in the orbit
and that should explain that hopefully
okay summert says do severe heat waves
like the one in europe affect the
functioning of nuclear plants
you see nuclear plants are built to a
very high degree of safety standards
the safety standards have to be very
stringent
when it comes to nuclear power plants
they have to take every single
dangerous scenario into consideration it
doesn't always happen sometimes you do
have accidents but typically they take
every single scenario into account what
if there is an earthquake
if there's an earthquake
will that affect our nuclear problem
they will have that scenario already
factored in when they build the nuclear
power power plant and they will have a
failed safe mechanism that if something
that this happens the nuclear reactor
can be quickly shut down
[Music]
similarly if there is flooding
if there is flooding for whatever reason
there should be a mechanism that will
take care of shutting the nuclear
reactor down immediately or as soon as
possible similarly there will be various
temperatures at which the nuclear power
plant operates
and if you see the temperature inside
the nuclear reactor it's incredibly high
right
a nuclear reactor is a very hot thing
and it it generates heat which is
generated in a controlled fashion
i think i have a video on this channel
in which i'm which is essentially a
nuclear physics crash course in which
i've explained in detail
how nuclear reactors work and more
so if you want to exactly understand how
it is take a look at the video i think
it's called nuclear physics crash course
on this channel whenever you get the
time take a look so nuclear reactors
produce heat
that heat is controlled you have these
cadmium rods that you insert into the
nuclear reactor to slow down the process
and to control the heat so the more
cadmium rods you insert
the cooler the reactor gets it gets
and if you remove some of them it gets
hotter so that's how you control the
nuclear reaction and
that heat is then used to produce steam
to drive a turbine and that's how you
generate electricity from a nuclear
reactor that's typically roughly how it
happens so the heat inside a nuclear
reactor is incredibly high
and you can control it with cadmium rods
typically
so if you have a heat wave outside it's
not going to affect the nuclear reactor
it will have a minimal
minimal effect on the reactor what's a
heat wave like 5 degrees above normal 10
degrees above normal if you have
typically 30 degrees temperature in a
heat wave you may have 40 degrees
temperature or 45 degrees at the extreme
level i would imagine
a 15 degrees rise in the external
temperature makes no difference to the
running of the nuclear reactor as long
as you have the carbon control rods and
everything else in place it makes no
difference whatsoever
so there is a very high and very
stringent set of safety safety standards
that are typically applied to nuclear
reactors they take all these various
possibilities and factors into
consideration what can go wrong every
single thing that can go wrong they
would have factored it in
in the design and in the construction of
the nuclear reactor and therefore we
should not be worried about this
hopefully
yeah
so severe heat waves
would typically
have
negligible
effect on the functioning of a nuclear
reactor or a power power plant you have
nuclear reactors in deserts
i think last week i had shown one
somewhere
and in india you typically have hot
temperatures right india is a warmer
place than let's say europe
so if the average temperature
in europe in a certain region may be 25
in india it may be 30 degrees
or even 30 to 30 to 33 degrees and yet
indian nuclear reactors work just fine
so um
so the answer in brief is severe heat
the heat waves
would have a negligible or minimal
effect on the functioning of a nuclear
power plant
says
mitochondria produces energy in our body
through food
which keeps us energetic what happens to
this energy within the human body when a
person dies
as energy can neither be created nor
destroyed
so what are mitochondria the the
mitochondria are the
power plants
within our cells
in our bodies we have cells yes
and
most of these cells contain these
small power plants called mitochondria
these mitochondria they take various
chemicals etc
and they have these these not nuclear
reactions but chemical reactions going
on inside
and these chemical reactions are
exothermic reactions they produce heat
right
so
i think research has been done about the
temperatures of mitochondria
so the average temperature of the human
body is around 36 degrees celsius i
think yes
98 or so degrees fahrenheit if i'm not
mistaken
but if you take a cell and you go inside
the cell and measure the temperature of
the mitochondrion
it is i believe the average temperature
of mitochondria is about 55 degrees
centigrade
so they're quite hot
and they generate this heat that we need
to stay alive
and that's why our average temperature
is about 98 degrees fahrenheit 36 or so
degrees celsius right um
so
the mitochondria they don't produce
energy
they
see
we
consume food
we don't consume just about anything we
don't eat um
we we eat very specific kind of
substances right we only eat organic
material
plants or whatever protein people eat
meat and all that yeah
so we only eat certain kinds of things
only certain kind of things can be
digested we cannot eat stones
we cannot eat
soil
we can't eat wood
right we only eat certain kind of things
and those things are
they provide us the nutrients we need
and the nutrients the mitochondria need
in order to produce this heat
so it is not
producing energy it is
it is doing
chemical reactions that are exothermic
in nature and they release
heat
so they break down various chemical
bonds and the breaking of those chemical
bonds releases this heat radiation right
so it is not creating energy producing
energy it is transforming one kind of
one kind of
energy
the potential energy stored inside
chemical bonds into
heat energy it's transforming one kind
of energy into a different kind of
energy that is what these chemical
reactions do and that's what
microchondria do to keep us warm and
healthy
and this exists in all animals so every
animal whether you take a rabbit or a
cat or a deer or a kangaroo or a snake
they all have a certain temperature some
animals are cold-blooded like like
reptiles and all but let's talk about
mammals
warm blooded animals
so every animal has a certain average
temperature a certain average
temperature it needs to be healthy
and it depends on on the mitochondria
and the rate at which they do these
chemical reactions and all these various
factors
so let's say some animal dies
let's say
a poor unfortunate rabbit dies yeah what
happens
all the chemical reactions stop
for the chemical reactions to to happen
you need blood circulation the blood
uh supplies all the cells
with oxygen
without the oxygen cells die all the
chemical reactions stop
if an animal stops breathing even for 60
seconds or
two minutes i think
cellular death death starts happening
and the cells in the body
are in this very delicate state of
equilibrium as long as the blood flows
and the oxygen keeps coming in they keep
doing what they're supposed to do the
chemical reactions and all that and the
mitochondria keep on producing energy
other things
the moment
the moment the blood flow stops and they
become the cells become deprived of
oxygen within just a few minutes the
cells start breaking down there are
various enzymes within the cell that
start digesting the cellular tissues the
cell walls and all that
and
yeah that is an irreversible process
essentially
you
you can't revive a dead animal beyond
a few minutes of death let's say an
animal's heart stops if you don't revive
that animal within two three minutes or
maximum five minutes depending on the
temperature you cannot revive the animal
after that that's how it goes so what
happens to this energy
it the energy is transformed the the
body starts decomposing very rapidly
and then the chemical reactions
of a different kind happen
so the
chemical reactions that produce the heat
within the mitochondria they won't
happen anymore but the digestive
chemical reactions of the various
enzymes breaking down the body and the
various tissues that's what happens and
then
the
that's called the process of
decomposition
so the energy doesn't go anywhere it is
just the the material is transformed
into something else and it is then
i suppose reclaimed back into the earth
that's what happens
right
so that is the entire process of what
happens when
someone dies or some animal dies
swapnil mishra says was it a systematic
or human error that caused the demise of
the russian cosmonaut of the vladimir
komarov
who hit the earth with the speed of an
asteroid from space and burned to ashes
he did not quite burn to ashes he just
he was obliterated so this i don't
remember when this happened i think it
was in the 1960s
so vladimir komarov was a russian
cosmonaut they called them cosmonauts
i'm not sure if i should put that on the
screen anyway i don't do it
so uh
what happened is that he went up into
space and at that time uh the spacecraft
that they were
planning to send into orbit was not
quite well designed it had flaws it had
defects
and the astronauts knew it
there was another russian astronaut at
the time his name was yuri gagarin he
was a great russian hero the first human
being to go into space he was a test
pilot
he was a fighter pilot and a test pilot
typically astronauts are
typically taken from the air force they
are usually extremely good pilots
especially test pilots so that's what
judy gagarin was
possibly vladimir kumar if i'm not
mistaken maybe not but
so for this mission
it was actually yuri gagarin who was
supposed to go into space
right
and these guys knew
the the spacecraft is defective
it has not
uh it's not going to function well
and if yuri gagarin went to space it was
there was a high likelihood that he
would die
and for that reason vladimir kumar
volunteered to go himself instead of
yuri gagarin
and that's what happened he went into
space the launch happened fine
and he did a few orbits or whatever i'm
not sure what the exact story is apogee
perigee whatever happened
he did his mission in space and then it
was time to come back
to earth
and what happened is that the parachute
failed
so the spacecraft re-enters the
atmosphere at a certain angle
and then there is this heat shield that
protects the spacecraft from the
re-entry temperatures and after you come
down
to a certain altitude the
parachute is supposed to open typically
it's three large parachutes that break
the fall and eventually you come down
slowly and you
come back to earth with a gentle thump
but if the parachute doesn't open
you're gonna hit the ground at a very
very high speed
and unfortunately that's what happened
with vladimir kumarov the parachute
never opened and he slammed into earth
into the earth
at an incredible velocity and
yeah well
you can imagine how he died i'm sure it
was painless and
i hear
that there is
a recording
of the communications the last
communications
between vladimir kumarov and the ground
base
as this thing was happening
yeah
i think the recording may be available
on youtube or something like that
i believe the americans were
eavesdropping on what was happening and
maybe they were able to
intercept
the messaging
so yes
that's the unfortunate story of vladimir
kumarov it was human error
it was human incompetence that caused
his completely pointless and avoidable
death
the spacecraft was not designed properly
there were flaws there were problems and
yet because of the political pressure
they had to send
the spacecraft in space
into orbit before it was quite ready
it's a communist nation
it was the dictatorship of the
proletariat so you had to do what the
bosses told you even if it cost you your
life
so vladimir kumarov decided to go
himself instead of putting yuri gagarin
on the line
and that resulted in his death that is
what happened
and yeah
yeah unfortunate and sad story
okay myron says why do feather and stone
drop together from the same height
fall down on the ground at the same time
on the moon they do it on the earth too
in the right conditions
it's like this it's the it's just that's
just how gravity works
you take two bodies you drop them
towards this towards the planet towards
the ground they're gonna fall at the
same speed let's say you have a
an object that weighs 10 kilograms
and you have a different object that
weighs 10 grams you drop them from the
same altitude at the same time
they're gonna both reach the ground at
the exact same time
that's just how it works that is the law
of gravity right
and yet
when you take a stone and you take a
feather you drop the two the stone hits
the ground first the feather just floats
down slowly slowly slowly slowly slowly
why is that so
it's it's because of
uh
it's because of the atmospheric drag
we have air around us the feather has a
very small mass
and it's got a very large surface area
and that's why because of the
atmospheric drag
the feather comes down very very very
slowly it it's its journey towards the
ground is slowed down
by the by the atmosphere by the air
around us
but if you make a vacuum
let's say you create a vacuum chamber on
the earth forget about the moon you can
do it on earth
so you
take a big
beaker or a jar you take out all the all
the air from it create a vacuum and then
you drop a stone and a feather at the
same time
they're gonna they're gonna fall down at
the exact same time time
even on the earth and of course you can
do it on the moon if you can reach there
so that's how it works right
so
over here on earth it's because the
air and the
in the friction of the air that the
feather is slowed down because it is
it's got such a small mass in such a
large surface area that is the reason
they fall down at different times on the
moon or in vacuum on earth they're gonna
hit the ground at the exact same time
okay dr nishte says humans in today's
age
are very advanced in terms of technology
and healthcare
and yet there is no sure short treatment
of myopia and hyper
metropia
so myopia means short-sightedness and
hypermetropia means long-sightedness
people still need to wear spectacles and
that number is increasing i sometimes
think there is a spectacle company mafia
behind all this dependence on wearing
glasses
i think they don't want the cure to be
developed or to be revealed as by doing
so they might go out of business am i
right what's your opinion about this
i think
modern technology and healthcare has
progressed a lot has advanced a lot
but the problem is that it is all used
for commercial purposes
what is a good business model tell me to
permanently cure someone
or to make somebody dependent on your
medicines you're gonna make more money
if you
instead of permanently curing somebody
necessitate it for them to keep on
taking your medicine
in order to stay reasonably healthy but
the moment is they stop buying your
medicines they're gonna fall sick again
that is a much better business model
unfortunately
so it's the commercialized
commercialization of health care that is
causing this it's the capitalistic model
right capitalism
capitalism is about maximizing your
profits it's about growing your company
and growing your profits on a quarter
upon quarter basis
yeah
in finite profits on a finite planet
that's destroying the planet and that's
what is causing all these problems so
most of the illnesses and diseases that
people have today most of them are
lifestyle diseases
they can
be cured simply by changing your
lifestyle
there is diabetes there is obesity
which is all caused by
the lack of activity and the kind of
diet that you eat right
and then you have these uh
short-sightedness long-sidedness that
is again caused by reading too much too
close to your face or or staring at
screens all day yeah
and various the things there is there is
a
what is it called hypertension and so
many other lifestyle diseases they can
be cured
permanently just by changing your
lifestyle but it's so hard to change
your lifestyle and then you have things
like um
things like cancer
things like cancer and various other
things and
so they want us
to not be permanently cured of anything
once you have some condition
they want to keep on giving you
medicines for the rest of your life in
order to keep the condition under check
under control
so the business model is don't allow
anyone to be permanently cured of
anything
make every disease every illness every
condition
chronic mild but chronic as long as you
take medicines it's gonna be mild it's
gonna be a slight inconvenience but
nothing more you stop taking medicine
you're gonna die
so that is the the perfect business
model that they've found and that's how
it is especially in the west
you go to the u.s they have the most
ridiculous
uh
costs of healthcare
everybody needs to buy this incredibly
expensive insurance and every single
thing costs so much
right so that's how it is it's very
unfortunate that
healthcare has become a business
it's become completely commercialized
everything is commercialized
and and that's why we have this thing
it's it's it's not just a spectacle
company mafia it's it's a healthcare
mafia
and now in india also we are we are
seeing the same thing
you know people need to buy expensive
insurance
and uh a simple treatment can can cost a
course of rupees destroys entire
families and all that
that's how it is so india is again
following the same business model 20
years ago it was very different you
could go to a doctor
instead of prescribing medicines the
doctor would give you a small packet
with a few pills
you take those pills and you're done
with three days five days and you and
you're cured of whatever you you were
having but now they will write these
prescriptions you go to the pharmacy it
will cost you thousands of rupees
and it's a rinse and repeat kind of
thing
so yes it's it's a corporate mafia
that does not want people to be cured of
anything
once you are in the hospital they want
to maximize your stay there
and and extract as much money out of you
as they possibly can and that's how it
is it's very unfortunate
um they take this hippocratic oath they
will be ethical and they will cure
people but they do the exact opposite
so yes i agree with you doctor nishi
gong that's how the world has become and
that is very unfortunate
um
[Music]
and if i say something against
capitalism it doesn't mean that i am
pro-communism or pro-marxism or anything
like that but uh
this this model this business model is
just about exploiting people
it's about exploiting
seven eight billion people and making
money out of their lives
they want to keep you alive as long as
possible so that they can keep making
money out of you as long as you live
and that's why they want to extend your
life extend your lifespans right
but they want you to stay alive based on
all the pills that they are selling you
and whatever else they're telling you
very unfortunate
jasmine says
studies have shown that the expansion of
universe
is accelerating that does it mean it
will forever keep expanding and all the
stars and galaxies and dark spaces will
move away from each other and the whole
universe will die a cold death in a few
billion years
what does modern physics have to say
about that
well 13.8 billion years ago the entire
universe was compressed into a single
point point like zero dimensional space
possibly a singularity
then you have this expansion that
happened it's called the big bang
colloquially yeah the expansion happened
it's it's still happening
and from everything from all the data
that we have it is clear that the
expansion of space time is accelerating
so if we
extrapolate this
into the future
let's say 1 billion years into the
future 10 billion years and so on we
will find that eventually
and if we look at the edge of the
observable universe
we find that eventually this
acceleration of space-time becomes super
luminal
which means it exceeds
the speed of light which is allowed
in general relativity nothing can go
faster than the speed of light inside
space-time within space-time but
space-time itself can expand faster than
the speed of light so that's what we are
witnessing so more and more of the
universe is going
out of our sight
right it's expanding beyond where we can
see
so the observable universe is getting
smaller and smaller actually and in a
few billion years
only the milky way galaxy will be
visible to us everything else would have
been exponent would have
gone too far away for us to see
and it will be gone forever
and eventually what will happen even the
milky way
the expansion of space time will even
take the star stars
[Music]
it will pull the stars away
and the milky way itself will
succumb
to the expansion of space-time
eventually all we will be able to see is
our own solar system
and then if things continue the way they
are going
then even the solar system will be
pulled apart
eventually even atoms and molecules will
be pulled apart and nothing will remain
nothing will remain
so this is what is called the big rip
scenario everything is pulled apart even
atoms and molecules are pulled apart
and at the end
the all that is left is darkness and
increa and almost absolute zero
temperature
so this is one scenario
of the ultimate fate of our universe the
big grip
you know
but we're not sure if that's what's
going to happen perhaps we're in an
oscillating universe the universe
expands for some time and then something
makes it contract again and instead of a
big rip there is a big crunch
and
there is the reverse of the big bang
happens and then it oscillates again
that's another possibility i mean we
don't quite know
because we don't have sufficient data
and we don't understand the laws of
physics that well thus far we have a
very rudimentary
very rudimentary understanding of the
laws of physics
so yes that is one possible scenario the
big rip where everything disappears even
atoms and molecules are torn apart
and nothing nothing is left
the other scenario is something else
could happen and we could have a big
crunch
and time could go into in reverse in a
sense possibly
so yeah it's
these scenarios are currently
possible
and we don't quite know what is going to
be the ultimate fate of our universe
swapnil again
interesting question how does
transcranial magnetic simulation
stimulation
tms
or electromagnetic therapy cure extreme
clinical depression
so what is this transcranial magnetic
stimulation
it's where you create a magnetic field
with an electromagnet
and you place it on the surface of the
of the of the scalp
or near the scalp
and you are you are essentially
generating a magnetic field
by running
an electric current through this device
and this magnetic field
induces electric currents inside your
brain
through the process of
of induction
and
i think this effect goes a few
centimeters
into the skull into the brain
and it somehow seems to have some
beneficial effect
on
clinical depression
and other things
we are not quite sure of what exactly
happens and people
experience different kinds of effects
some people
have twitching of the face some people
have neck pain some people have nausea
some sometimes symptoms are more severe
some people have no symptoms whatsoever
and overall it seems that there is some
kind of a beneficial effect for people
who are uh suffering from either
clinical depression
or tinnitus you know the constant
drinking drinking that some people have
in their ears and so on so it seems to
alleviate some of these symptoms and
ameliorate
uh their condition in some cases
now people
some people have this but we're not
quite sure how it works
because
the organ
in the human body that is the least
understood is the brain
we have these psychiatrists etc who say
that they they're they're scientists
they're not doing science they're doing
voodoo they don't know how the brain
works we don't have the least idea of
how the brain works how the mind works
where consciousness comes from we don't
understand these things
and
once again when you when you're doing
this tms therapy
it's not possible to study the brain
waves and see what's happening within
the brain because the electromagnetic
field that you're creating
and the magnetic field that's going into
the brain it's going to interfere with
the instruments so we don't know what's
happening in there
but yes it seems to alleviate some
symptoms and and make people feel better
people who are especially depressed and
in some cases
people who have their eyes closed and
they are subjected to tms
they seem to experience supernatural
phenomena like something else is in the
room with them something that is not
quite human
so most people feel
good like it's some benevolent presence
but some people are scared of their wits
when this happens so yeah there are
these weird phenomena that happen and we
don't quite know how what is happening
how does it affect the brain we know
that there is electrical activity in the
brain we know that
the brain is a bunch of nerve tissue
lots
billions trillions of
synapses and nerve connections right
it's it's it's the it's a natural neural
network you have all these electrical
signals that are going around
all the time
and when you apply a magnetic field to
that it's going to uh
have some effect
on the brain on the electrical signals
and maybe that's that's what's causing
these symptoms but we don't quite know
what's happening yeah so if you ask me
how does it cure things first of all i'm
not sure if it cures everything
and secondly what is the mechanism
well some kind of electromagnetic
magnetic mechanism it's inducing a
current in the brain
in some way
and if you're inducing a current in the
brain it's going to affect the nervous
signals and all that so so that is
roughly what's happening but what are
the specific details we don't quite know
because we don't know the functioning of
the brain itself
so yeah that's what it is
okay suril jain says
um
dear sir okay two questions
please tell me what is what is the 3d
shape of a black hole is it a sphere in
shape or what
and secondly suppose we create a mini
black hole in a lab let's say one
centimeter in diameter
then what if my
what if i put my finger into it what
will happen
okay let's take question number one
first
what is the three-dimensional shape of a
black hole
so if it is a non-rotating black hole a
schwarzschild black hole is going to be
a perfect
sphere all right if it is not a rotating
black hole
so a non-rotating black hole is called a
schwarzschild black hole
that is going to be a perfect perfect
sphere
but
if your black hole is rotating in this
direction of that
in that case it will not be a perfect
sphere it's going to be a squashed
sphere
it's going to be oblate in shape
what does oblate look like let us google
that oblate
what does oblate look like let us put
that on the screen so that you get a
good idea
right so this is what an oblate shape
looks like
it's a spheroid
there you have it
so when you have a black hole that is
rotating it's going to be like like the
shape of the earth slightly squashed
sphere
and if it is rotating fast it's going to
be more squashed if it is rotating
slowly it is going to be less squashed
so that in short is what the shape of a
black hole is like
not rotating it's perfectly spherical if
it is rotating it's going to be a
squashed sphere it's going to be oblate
now second
second question suppose we create a mini
black hole in a lab let's say it's one
centimeter in diameter and i'm going to
put my finger into it what's going to
happen
your black hole is going to grow in size
and you're going to lose a finger
so if you place any
massive object any material into a black
hole the black hole is going to absorb
it
and it's going to grow in size
you put your finger in there you're
going to lose your finger your fingers
never coming out
yeah that's what happens
uh if you
put your finger beyond that black holes
event horizon that is the point of no
return that's a boundary of no return
you go you go there it's not coming back
and the black hole will get attached to
your finger it's gonna
it's gonna essentially try to suck more
in
and since it's it's a one centimeter
black hole if a black hole is one
centimeter in diameter it's going to be
a massive thing it's going to be really
really really massive you go close
enough to it it's going to suck you
entirely into it and you're going to get
spaghettified
you know really really pulled pulled out
spaghettification so depending on the
size and all that you're going to have
different effects but yeah it's not a
good idea if you create a black hole in
the lab if you're able to do that please
don't do that and if you do it please
stay far away
because it's going to suck you right in
and you're never coming out and before
you go in there and while going in there
it's not going to be a pleasant
experience for you all right
so yeah that's what it is
abhijit says
humorously it's said that without
engineers science is just a philosophy
engineers deal with with messy reality
of the universe
as per you what's science engineering
technology in philosophy
why is the ultimate degree in something
a phd a philosophy degree
science is about studying the universe
it's about studying nature i mean you
can put take a subset of the universe
and study that
so biology is a science it's it's about
applying chemistry
to
the the principles and laws of chemistry
to living materials that's essentially
biology so to to do biology well you
have to understand chemistry and to
understand chemistry well you have to
understand physics to do physics well
you don't understand mathematics
and so on so science is the study of the
universe in its various forms in various
subsets of the universe
engineering
is about taking the understanding of
science that we have and applying it
into creating things into creating
technology
so engineering is applied to science
it's applied physics mostly but yeah you
have bioengineering and chemical
engineering and whatnot yeah so
engineering is about applying science
into creating things into building
things
and what in the output
is technology so you create new
technology you develop new technologies
through engineering rocket scientists
are all engineers
they're not really scientists they're
engineers they understand physics they
understand aerodynamics they understand
the chemistry of various kinds of fuels
and all that and they build rockets
so so they build things so rocket
scientists are engineers
so that is science there is engineering
there is technology philosophy is a
whole different thing
philosophy is the study of
of the universe in a sense
but philosophy is also the study of
things like ethics and morality
yeah ethics and morality and right and
wrong and things like that
so philosophy is a whole different thing
science is a subset of philosophy
in philosophy you don't have beliefs
you have logic
philosophy is is
logical
you take logic out of it it's no longer
philosophy
so you can have things that like
like like uh ethics and morality but if
you want to do philosophy you do it in a
logical fashion
and then there are things like religion
and spirituality and whatnot which i
can't really define properly because you
ask any person everybody will have a
different definition of that so these
are things you can't really define but
philosophy has is something that obeys
logic
now why is the ultimate degree in
something a phd a philosophy degree i
don't know why it's a philosophical
degree
you think the i don't think the phd is
the ultimate achievement a person can
have
i know lots of phds who
well what can i say about them you know
see to acquire a phd
you need to solve you need to take up a
certain problem and you do write a
thesis
now if you look at the quality of
various phd thesis you will see that
it's not
always
the best quality
and
just by solving a certain problem or
working on a problem for three to five
years you're not going to master the
subject
so having a phd
is no guarantee that the person is the
is a master of his field or her field
right
so
why is the ultimate degree in something
a phd or philosophy degree it's just
tradition
it's something that's come out of the
western education system
there was a time when philosophy was the
highest thing before science became a
thing in the west
so i think this tradition continued and
that's why we just keep following it
blindly
and that's how it is yeah
all right
karthik says if a tree falls in a forest
and no one is around to hear it
does it make a
sound let me ask an analogous question
when i'm not looking at the moon
does it still exist
let's say we do an experiment we
instruct every single human being on the
earth
to simultaneously look down at the floor
on the ground
it means that
for a certain period of time
not a single human being
is observing or looking at the moon
what does it mean then does the moon
cease to exist for that period of time
if nobody is observing it does it still
exist that's the kind of question you're
asking well
it still exists let's say a tree falls
in a forest and there is no one to see
it or no one to hear it but let's see
i've kept
a cctv camera there
so the event happens nobody observes
observes it but the cctv camera records
it and three months later i can go there
i can open up the camera take out the sd
card or whatever it is and then see the
footage
in my
laptop so the event did happen
and i can hear the sound later on the
recorded sound
so that's how it is sir if a tree falls
in a forest and no one is around to hear
it it still does fall and it still does
make a sound
and you can record that and see it a
hundred years later if you want
yeah
so yeah it's it's a kind of
philosophical question you're asking but
that is the answer it it does make a
sound and it does actually happen so
even if there is no observer to observe
the event you can have a recording
and that recording can serve as an
observer
but what if you have no recording does
it really happen well i don't know
it see the entire
uh planet the entire universe is
interconnected
and
entangled in some way
so i think events do happen even if
nobody observes them they do happen
all right i think that brings us to the
end of the questions that i have for
today
now let's take some questions from the
live chat
we seem to have ended a little earlier
today then so let's take some questions
from the live chat
so ishaan says maybe if you did not see
the recording until you see the
recording it doesn't make a sound
well the recording is of an event that
happened in the past
and that recording is available for
anyone to see at any point in time
so the sound already happened it was
recorded it was captured and it can be
played back whenever you want so
that's the that's the thing right that's
uh that's the argument
all right what do we have
concept of fish falling from the sky
interesting question
this phenomenon does happen
it is observed all across the world
it's a very rare phenomenon but you have
these you have reports of this happening
all across the world
at various points in time yeah
fish falling from the sky frogs falling
from the sky
so how does this happen
there is a phenomenon called a water
spout let me put that on the screen if
there is an image of that available
water spout let's see what a water spout
looks like shall we
this is what a water spout looks like
it's essentially a tornado you know what
a tornado is
the whirling
air phenomenon
so when a tornado happens over water
a tornado is a
it's a phenomenon that's caused by
extreme low pressure and that's what
causes air to swirl and it sucks things
up
if you see a tornado operating
on on ground
then you will see that it sucks things
up it sucks it it pulls trees into the
air it it pulls buildings into the air
cars into the air it it has the effect
of sucking things upwards
now if a tornado happens over water
over the ocean it's gonna suck things up
and what's in the ocean you have fish in
the ocean
right or in a pond in a lake or whatever
so all these wonderful little fish will
be sucked upwards they will go into the
air
and eventually what goes up is to come
down
so these fish they go into the into the
air up into the cloud and then the cloud
moves somewhere else and
some somehow it may happen that it falls
on the ground
and so people report this phenomenon of
fish
falling from the sky it's typically a
fish that were sucked upwards in by a
water spout by a tornado that happened
over the ocean or over a lake or a river
and then it deposited the fish on ground
and so people saw fish or frogs or
whatever falling from the sky and they
think it's some great almond from women
from the gods which is not quite the
case
all right
all right what do we have
aurobindo seal says
what if somebody dies in outer space
body cannot decompose so will the body
float in space forever
say you have an astronaut who is wearing
a space suit
and for whatever reason hypothetically
yeah this hypothetical astronaut dies in
space let's say
will the body not decompose
it will decompose
the moment
blood stops flowing
the cells and the tissues in the body
will be starved of oxygen
so the regular normal process normal
chemical reactions will immediately end
and then various enzymes will start
decomposing the body they will start
breaking down the cellular tissues the
cell walls and whatnot
and that is the process of decomposition
you also have lots of bacteria in the
body in the in the gut in the elementary
elementary canal in the intestines
once
the body dies they start eating up the
body
so even if somebody dies in outer space
the body will decompose
if you are wearing a space suit it will
decompose within the spacesuit if a
person is exposed in in outer space
then first of all the person will die of
lack of oxygen
and then the decomposition process will
happen anyway
right so that's how it goes i don't know
i'm getting lots of questions about
dying and decomposition but
well that's what it is
all right
let us see something else why are quest
i'm not getting questions about
democracy and politics
today is
a science day let's talk about science
uh where we are israel india please
science today is science
let's see if i have some good questions
shiv satya says
tell your opinion about the aerial
school ufo incident in africa
what is the aerial school
ufo incident
um i i had heard about
school
and kids and ufo okay let's just google
it aerial school ufo
a real school ufo
what is that
so once again
this is what it is it is a report by
some people
some kids perhaps
who reported seeing something
but once again there is no photograph
i mean this is just some some kind of
image somebody has made up
i will be convinced when i see actual
photographic or video evidence or an
actual interview with an alien or a
captured ufo or spacecraft some concrete
evidence somebody makes a claim it
doesn't convince me sometimes you have
mass hallucinations
that phenomenon has been observed in the
past mass solution hallucinations lots
of people believe the same thing they
all hallucinate something together it's
happened these are various psychological
phenomena that happen so as far as i
don't have actual evidence yeah i know
some kids are talking about it in this
video
it still doesn't convince me
unfortunately
i need to see
incontrovertible evidence in order to be
convinced and yeah
all right what else do we have
who is virgil grissom
i regret that i don't know who this
that is unfortunately
uh maybe i'll try and look it up in the
future
okay
karan says what will be the shape of our
galaxy when it will merge with andromeda
galaxy in the future we don't know
there's gonna be a nice gravitational
dance tango the two galaxies will come
together
they will pass through each other some
stars will be thrown out flung out in
different directions they'll go far away
then over time they'll come back so
it'll be a merger process maybe
eventually you will ever
eventually you may have a spiral galaxy
or maybe a spheroid oblate galaxy we're
not quite sure
we would have to do various computer
simulations to see how
what actually happens
i have seen certain videos of computer
simulations of galaxies merging it's a
messy process
and eventually you have this
spherical or spheroid oblate kind of
galaxy that emerges out of it over time
over a few billion years so maybe that's
what happens but we are not 100 sure
because there are so many parameters
involved
and
so we have two spiral galaxies merging
most likely something that looks
oblate or spheroidal most likely but we
cannot be 100 sure of that
okay what else do we have
um
is a reincarnation
a mass
halogenation
look
i think you're trying to say if it is
mass hallucination look i don't know
i have
no understanding of of reincarnation or
supernatural things you know
reincarnation is not a scientific thing
at all
uh and it's not a mass thing
so we have these claims of so that some
people make that they can remember a
past life it's not
something that multiple people are
remembering right it's just one person
remembering an individual alleged past
life so
there's no way of proving it right
there is no scientific way of of
correlating
one consciousness or one in one person
with somebody who died earlier there is
no actual way to
100 prove that
so yeah so it's it's not something that
is accepted by science for obvious
reasons
all right where are we democracy again
i'm not answering questions about
democracy today
uh right what do we have
what are the latest findings of the
james webb space telescope what do you
make out of it uh i haven't been keeping
up with all the latest findings i think
there was a set of images that was
that were released
some time ago i think i had spoken about
that so what we are seeing is we are
seeing much better images
uh when it comes to certain galaxies
that were seen in the past facing much
sharper images and all that so it's
clear that this telescope is much
much
more superior than the hubble space
telescope
and
it seems to be discovering
a new furthest galaxy ever seen almost
every week
so it's still a process that's happening
right now i have not
kept up with all the latest news in the
past couple of weeks maybe i will do it
and maybe i can answer this question in
a little more detail maybe next week or
so yeah but yeah it seems to be just
making new discoveries every week
every week some new galaxies discovered
that seems to be the furthest or most
distant galaxy ever discovered so yeah
we just in the beginning phase of this
and it's going to discover a whole lot
of stuff that is going to change our
understanding
of the universe so yeah it's very
exciting i'm very
happy to see this very excited to see
what else comes in the future
all right
what else do we have
[Applause]
what do we have what do we have let's
see something interesting
does light travel at the same speed in
all directions yes it travels at the
same speed in all directions in vacuum
or in any medium
so if if you take glass for instance the
speed of light in glass
is the same in all directions but it is
less than the speed of light in vacuum
so light travels slower through glass
then it travels through vacuum and
similarly with water
once again it's it travels slower in
water then it travels through vacuum but
it travels at the same speed in all
directions all directions inside
water
vardhan says what will happen if all
hydrogen on the sun gets used up
well it depends uh
once you run out of hydrogen you're
gonna start fusing helium once you start
once you run out of helium you're gonna
start fusing heavier elements and
every star has a certain limit up to
which it can fuse things if a star is
about roughly 20 20 times the mass of
the sun it can keep fusing heavier and
heavier elements
until
it starts producing iron at the core and
the fusion
the process the fusion process that
creates iron
it absorbs it it consumes more energy
than it releases releases
and that is going to cause the collapse
of that star
and if the star is about 20 times or so
the math the sun it's going to
eventually
collapse go supernova and give you a
black hole at the the center
but in the case of the sun
the sun is not a big star it's it's a
small small little star yeah it's not a
very particularly large star so what
will happen with the sun
is at the end of all this fusion process
when all the hydrogen is used up the
helium is used up at the end it's going
to stop at carbon
it's not going to be able to fuse or
create any elements heavier than carbon
so at the end of its life cycle
it's going to give off the outer layers
of its atmosphere and it's going to be
left as a white dwarf what is a white
dwarf it is an extraordinarily hot
carbon nucleus crystalline carbon
nucleus you know what crystalline carbon
is called it's called diamond
so white dwarf is an extraordinarily
hot
massive
diamond
that's what it is
and after many many billions of years
it's going to cool down and become a
black dwarf
that is the ultimate
fate of the sun
right
right where else do we have
no i'm not answering questions about
souls
can there be a possibility of having a
human civilization in every galaxy
it may be possible
human civilization human like
civilization humanoid
beings it is possible the probability i
would say is nonzero but we don't
exactly know what it is because we don't
have sufficient data
the only data point of life
that we have
is our planet
so we only have one known data point in
the entire observable universe
i would say that the probability will be
there i think
life
definitely would exist in
all galaxies or most galaxies
and even intelligent life but
human civilization i i don't know
human-like possible
but
once again i i i cannot really answer
the question because i don't have enough
data
no scientist nobody can answer the
question i would say
from my gut feeling it's possible that
there will be life in other
other star systems other galaxies maybe
even human like life but we don't know
for sure we will know only when we
discover it for the first time
right
what will happen if the rotation of the
earth slows down or increases if the
rotation of the earth
slows down the days will become slower
will become longer and then
obviously that that sort of process if
it happens will take time
and as the days go become longer
uh the tides will change the the earth
moon system will be affected the
circadian circadian cycles of living
beings animals birds insects will be
affected and so on
and if the rotation increases for
whatever reason the days will become
shorter instead of 24 hours you'll have
22 hours 19 hours whatever in the past
it was like that
the earth's rotation speed was not
always the same in the past
maybe a couple of billion or so years
ago i think the length of a day on earth
was about 19 hours which means the
rotation speed was faster
and so on so it's a process of change
the only thing that remains constant is
change itself
and depending on the speed of rotation
the length of the day will change and
life will have to adapt
according to that
but obviously it happens so slowly that
life is able to adapt
right
okay sahil says aren't hydrogen cars
risky as hydrogen is highly combustible
why is india betting on it rather than
other than lithium batteries
um
yes hydrogen is indeed combustible but
if you develop safe technology then
it'll be fine even petrol is combustible
obviously it's not as combustible or
volatile as hydrogen
but
but hydrogen is something that you can
produce cheaply
through electrolysis of readily
available water which is available in
incredibly abundant quantities
so it makes sense to explore that
possibility yeah of course there is a
risk in that everything has a certain
risk
so you have to mitigate the risk you
have to develop technologies that make
it safe to use
right
lithium batteries destroy the atmo the
environment
you have to dig the earth you have to
pull lithium out it produces a huge
amount of waste
it's not
good for the environment in the long run
that's why hydrogen makes more sense
you don't want to destroy the planet in
in our in our request for
batteries right
so that's why hydrogen is a long-term
sustainable solution much more
sustainable sustainable than lithium-ion
ion batteries
it has this problem it's highly
combustible
so we will have to develop the
appropriate technologies to mitigate
that problem but obviously hydrogen
makes much more sense
because we are not destroying
the planet in order to
produce hydrogen the only waste product
that we are
producing
to produce hydrogen is oxygen
which is not really a bad thing right so
that is the reason why uh there is this
emphasis there is this push towards
trying to see whether we can use
hydrogen and adopt it on a mass scale
right what else we have are we done
i think there are lots of questions
akshay says why
does mercury despite being small have
more gravity than the moon
because it is more massive than the moon
it is small but it is not as small as
the moon
if you see if mercury has more gravity
than the moon
i i as of right now i don't remember
exactly what the mass of mercury is and
what the mass of the moon is let's say
you have two bodies body a a and body b
if body b has more gravity it means its
mass is greater than body a it's as
simple as that
so in case mercury
has more gravity than the moon it means
it is more massive
it may be small but the moon is smaller
all right
right
okay let's take
one more question
is the earth's weight constant
overall the earth's weight is more or
less the same
uh
i am sure that there is a certain rate
at which the earth is very slowly very
slowly losing a small amount of it its
atmosphere
every second there's a small rate of
change
but that is obviously negligible so i
would say that the weight of the earth
is more or less constant
the the solid
part of the earth and the liquid part of
the earth is
i'm sure if you add it up add it all up
together
it would be very similar to what it was
maybe a billion years or so ago so for
all intents and purposes
the weight of the earth is indeed
constant as far as we are concerned
obviously if you take a time period of
of
four billion years
the age of the earth is about four
roughly four and a half billion years
in that time i am sure it's more or less
constant maybe a little bit of mass may
have been lost maybe through collisions
with other
solar system objects
uh
comets comets asteroids maybe there was
an ancient collision with another body
which gave rise to the moon so if you
disregard that the mass is more or less
constant right
okay i think we are done for today
we are almost at the two hour mark so
thank you very much all of you thank you
for the great questions
always great fun talking to you and i
will see you in tomorrow's session
in less than 24 hours from now until
then take care
and good night good day